Guide to the Stephen Longstreet Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Stephen Longstreet papers
1925-1990
YCAL MSS 262
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.35
(6 boxes)
The Stephen Longstreet Collection consists of four types of material: a heavily illustrated typescript of an undated and unpublished book project; 130 drawings in various formats and media; seven collages; and a small group of ephemeral items. The focus of the collection is Longstreet's observation of jazz culture, particularly as it engaged African Americans. He lived in cities on all three American coasts, as well as major cities in Europe, where he recorded scenes and people in local clubs, bars, and music and dance halls.
Longstreet, Stephen, 1907-2002
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stephen Longstreet, 1965-1992. The portraits of Gertrude Stein and Ezra Pound were transferred from the Yale University Library's Arts of the Book Collection in 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Stephen Longstreet (1907-2002)
The artist, novelist, and screenwriter Stephen Longstreet was born in New York City on April 18, 1907, and raised in New Brunswick, NJ. His birth name was Chauncey Weiner, a surname shortened from the family name Weiner-Longstrasse; as a youth he changed his first name to Henry and in the early 1940s became known as Stephen Longstreet. He began his career as a graphic artist in New York by publishing cartoons and vignettes in periodicals such as the New Yorker, Vanity Fair, Saturday Evening Post, and Colliers, then went on to write radio, television, and film scripts. Longstreet wrote, ghostwrote, compiled, and edited nearly 140 books between 1936 and 1999, which were published under the name Stephen Longstreet, as well as his pseudonyms Thomas Burton, Paul Haggard, David Ormsbee, Henri Weiner, Stephen Weiner-Longstreet, and Philip Wiener. Many of his early drawings appeared with the signature "Henri." Longstreet married Ethel Godoff (1909-1999) in Brooklyn in 1935; they had two children. He died in Los Angeles on February 20, 2002.
Longstreet wrote both novels and non-fiction works. Most of the latter were not reviewed kindly, with reviewers questioning his accuracy of content and reliability of sources. Perhaps his most notable hoax was Nell Kimball: Her Life as an American Madam, by herself, edited and with an introduction by Stephen Longstreet (1970). He claimed to have received a manuscript memoir from Kimball (1854-1934), a well-traveled prostitute and New Orleans madam, tried in vain to find a publisher for it in the 1930s, and then held on to her manuscript when she died. After citing it as primary source material for his own books Sportin' House: a History of New Orleans Sinners and the Birth of Jazz (1965) and The Wilder Shore: a Gala Social History of San Francisco's Sinners and Spenders, 1849-1906 (1968), Longstreet sold the manuscript to Macmillan Publishing. Kimball's autobiography received positive notices in newspapers and mass-market periodicals, but academics found too many close parallels in narrative and language to the works of Herbert Asbury (1889-1963), and shortly, both the text and the madam were found to be Longstreet's fabrications. The Wilder Shore itself was then revealed to have been paraphrased from Asbury's book The Barbary Coast (1933).
Scope and Contents
The Stephen Longstreet Papers consists of four types of material with which he described and illustrated his experiences during the Harlem Renaissance and the Jazz Age: a heavily illustrated typescript of an unpublished book project, 130 drawings in various formats and media, seven collages, and a small group of ephemeral items.
Arrangement
The Stephen Longstreet Papers is organized into five series: Series I. "From 'The Lost Generation' to 'The Grapes of Wrath,'" (1990, undated); Series II, Additional Papers (1948-1976); Series III, Harlem Sketch Books (1925-1939, undated); Series IV, Drawings (1925-1975, undated); and Series V, Stage Backdrop Collages (1952-1955, undated).
Jazz in art; Jazz musicians; Jazz -- Pictorial works; Collages (visual works); Drawings (visual works) -- 20th Century; Drawings -- United States -- 20th Century; Figures (representations); Illustrations (layout features); Portraits; Watercolors (paintings); Longstreet, Stephen, 1907-2002
- "From 'The Lost Generation' to 'The Grapes of Wrath'", 1990, undated; Series I; 6
  Arrangement
  Arranged by page number as assigned by author.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. holds 183 pages of drawings and essays by Stephen Longstreet. Described by the author as "A Graphic Work in Progress" and "a personal recall that attempts to reappraise one man's cut of pie of his world [sic], close up," it is a series of short writings from memory, embellished with a few historical facts, and laced with quotes from other writers and celebrities. The compositions are illustrated with his impressionistic sketches. Longstreet's aim, he stated in his introduction, was to provide a more realistic telling of the 1920s and 1930s in response to the "myths and legends" put forth by other authors in the 1940s; he said that his friend William Faulkner had encouraged him to write "a truer version of those times." The manuscript was organized by Longstreet into three sections: "Introduction" (pages 1-8); "The Lost Generation" (pages 9-65, covering the 1920s); and "Years of Wrath: the Great Depression" (pages 66-96, covering the 1930s). He ends with the specter of World War II. The text itself is undated, but it was enclosed in a paper wrapper made by the author and dated May 16, 1990. It does not appear to have ever been published.
  The work consists primarily of xerographic copies of Longstreet's drawings and typed pages of text; some of the images having been enhanced with black felt-tip marker, and a few of the pages are the original typescripts. The text pages, each of which contains a discrete story, essay, or vignette, were attached with white paper tape to a facing-page illustration. This had the effect of creating ninety-two gatherings which he arranged and numbered in pencil. Not all of the drawing-text sets are present: pages 9, 10, 12, 14, 18, 26, 29-32, 41, 43, 47-48, and 52 are lacking, and there are several additional pages that were later inserted (i.e. page 7 and 7A). Because there is no linear narrative to the work, and each text page is independent from the other, it is not possible to tell what content was held on the missing parts.
  Longstreet's introduction is somewhat autobiographical and gives a brief résumé of his early employment with New York periodicals and some of his experiences in Hollywood. The second and third sections have lively and sometimes humorous descriptions of people, events, and situations in locations including Paris, New York (with specific writings on the Chinatown and Lower East Side immigrant communities), Washington, Chicago, Spain, England, and Japan. In addition to his stories, Longstreet created both visual and written portraits of notable personalities such as Collette, Faulkner, Gandhi, Garbo, Joyce, Maugham, Orwell, Stravinsky, Stein, and Toklas. His topical net is cast wide enough to include an image of a Harvard-Yale football game.
  - Cover wrapper, 1990 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Introduction, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Lost Generation [1920s], undated (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Years of Wrath [1930s], undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
- Additional Papers, 1948-1976; Series II; 3
  Series II, Additional Papers (1948-1976), holds twelve ephemeral items sent to the Yale by Longstreet: one playbill, seven exhibition and lecture invitations, one hand-colored photocopy, a pair of plate proofs from his book Knaurs Jazzlexikon (Munich, 1957), and a two-color poster for an exhibition of Longstreet's drawings (tekeningen) in Breda, Netherlands, in 1976.
  - Ephemera, 1948-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Proofs of plates from Knaurs Jazzlexikon, 1957
  - Poster from exhibition in Breda, Netherlands, 1976
- Harlem Sketch Books, 1925-1939, undated; Series III; 2
  Organized into two subseries: Sketch book one; and Sketch books two and three.
  Series III contains fifty loose drawings that arrived at the library in two envelopes labeled by Longstreet as "1st sketch book" and "2d + 3d sketch books." On each he added "remains of Harlem sketch books – covers destroyed by insects + storage." The drawings were made on 8½ by 11 inch sheets of paper. Longstreet's concept of "sketch book" is not that of the classic sketchbook used by artists: here the papers are of varying types and hues, and most likely were never bound together. (They may have once been gathered in portfolios, and it would have been those covers that were destroyed.) The drawings in this series closely resemble in size, paper stock, and theme, a group in Series IV, Box 4, but Longstreet had mounted those works on larger-size supports for presentation.
  Though Longstreet called them "Harlem sketch books," the images are non-specific as to place, although many could have been made in or of Harlem. As is the case throughout the collection, the dates given by Longstreet may not be accurate. One example is the two drawings now in the second and third sketch books folder, "Country club – polite jazz" and "Gala with mild jazz music," both dated 1939, which he later photocopied and mounted together as one image (now in Series IV) titled "Country club dance, Tuxedo Park NY" and dated September 1929. Because his images and themes are fairly universal, Longstreet was apparently able to repurpose them with ease: the drawing "Uptown," in the same Harlem sketch book, has a label taped to the verso which indicates that it was used as an illustration in The Wilder Shore, his 1968 book about San Francisco that describes the city between the years 1849 and 1906.
  - Sketch book one
    - Band manager/Old jazz composer, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bessie Smith, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Blues shouter, New Orleans, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Blues singer, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Bunk" Johnson, quick sketch, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Bunk" Johnson tries a stick, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Club date, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Cool sax, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Death of a jazzman/Goodbye, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dedicated, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The devil makes music, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Duet, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Flapper, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - A gig, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Gin/The drinker, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - A good woman is hard to keep/A good woman is hard to get, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Harlem jam session, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Jam session, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Latin", undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Night club, only the bottle is real, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Recording star, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - St. Louis woman, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - The shouter, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Shuffling along/Speakeasy music, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Singer, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Solo, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - String genius, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Toy horn, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sketch books two and three
    - At liberty, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Black Harlem/How long my Lord, how long?, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Combo /Longhair jam, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Cotton Club piano bar, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Country club – polite jazz, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 88 keys, Dice [?] Club Harlem, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Gala with mild jazz music, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harlem [street scene], 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harlem [dancers], 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harlem boy/The city boy, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Harlem fast dance/Dance team, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Horn man, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Jail house, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lonely blues, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Louie Armstrong, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - New Orleans, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Slap bass, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Solo, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Uptown, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Wish I could shimmy like my sister Kate, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - The Wolverines, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Young woman blues, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Drawings, 1925-1975, undated; Series IV; 6.26; (4 boxes)
  Organized into six subseries: New Orleans, Chicago, New York, Portraits, Miscellaneous Jazz Subjects, and General Subjects; arranged alphabetically by title thereunder.
  Series IV holds eighty artworks. Because of the variety of sizes of paper Longstreet used, the drawings were grouped and housed in four sizes of boxes, a factor which slightly influenced the subseries arrangement. Within each subseries, the drawings are filed alphabetically by title. As in Series III, Longstreet sometimes captioned his works on both their front and back, so both titles appear in the box and folder list.
  The drawings in Series IV continue the imagery and themes mentioned previously, and primarily portray band members and soloists, vocalists, dancers, and café society in various places related to jazz music. Added here, though, are a set of portraits of specific celebrities that Longstreet encountered during his lifetime; perhaps the most unusual faces, in the context of the collection, are those of Pablo Picasso, Ezra Pound, Elvis Presley, and Gertrude Stein. Longstreet's media are the same as in the earlier series, with two exceptions: a Cubist-style collage titled "Jazz at Monterey (Calif)," and his "Whites in Harlem, fashionable set," which was overpainted with acrylic (it is, as well, one of the few works with second drawing on the verso). The series holds several of Longstreet's strikingly spare and linear black ink images of jazz types, such as "The Bop boys," and "Shimmy." His note on "Work song" says that it was once owned by the legendary jazzman King Oliver (1885-1938). "Detroit Breadline '32" is a xerographic print, and the image appears again on page 4A in his Series I project.
  Longstreet made notes on the verso of some of the drawings in the series. One example is in the Chicago subseries; on the verso of "Al Capone roadhouse Chicago" he wrote, "Jazz owes a great deal to Al Capone. He controled [sic] a great deal of Chicago's cafes, clubs and the country side road houses. In need of bands he had hired a great many of the jazzmen up from the south looking for gigs. The white boys heard this new music and brought jazz over to white bands forming and taking on much of the styles of the black ways of playing."
  At the end of the series are three images unrelated to music: two are courtroom scenes and one is a street scene in London.
  - New Orleans
    - Bourbon St., 1926 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Bourbon St., New Orleans, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Delta, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Lonely Girl Blues, New Orleans, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mardi Gras party, New Orleans, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - New Orleans bar band/A fast finish, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Original Dixieland man/When the Saints Go Marching In, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Spam band, New Orleans street group, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - They're comin in the window, New Orleans, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Chicago
    - Al Capone roadhouse Chicago, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Chicago school/Chicago school white jazz, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Circus jazz/Barnum & Bailey Circus in Chicago, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Private party, Chicago/Late company, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Reflections, Chicago, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Rent party – Chicago, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Tailgate/Circus music/Carnival horn, 193 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - New York
    - Ballroom, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Band singer/at café society uptown, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Brass solo, Harlem, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Depression, Harlem, a good girl gone, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Harlem/Blues singer, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Harlem burial/Death of a jazzman, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Harlem horn man, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Harlem/Teenage music lover, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Harlem trio, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Honky tonk singer/Harlem, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Hot trio, 1929/1942 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Kid band, Harlem, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Reefer man on the guage [?], Harlem, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Savoy ballroom, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Times Square, NYC, Duke Ellington men, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Trio, Village Vanguard, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Whites in Harlem, fashionable set, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Portraits
    - Louie Armstrong, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Josephine Baker, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Josephine Baker [three drawings mounted as one], 1927 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - W.C. Fields during the filming of "My Little Chickadee", 1940 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Dizzy [Gillespie]/At Bop City New York, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Al Jolson acting a small scene in "The Jolson Story", 1946 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - [Pablo] Picasso from life on interview, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Ezra Pound, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Elvis [Presley] – the last drawing – a year before he died, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Gertrude Stein, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Hollywood Bowl (Pola Negri, Louella Parsons, Paul Lucas), 1935 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous jazz subjects
    - Jazz at Monterey (Calif), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - At the Lighthouse [Hermosa Beach, CA?], undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Banjo, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Beginner brown/Early starter, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Black and white, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Death of a jazz man, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Doghouse, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - End of a jazz man, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Jam/A Jam, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Late at night/Blue boy, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Long hair, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Married life, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Negro church play/"Rise Up Lazarus" a Spiritual, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Powerhouse, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - A reed man, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - The riff, 1925 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - San Francisco – the pad, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Singer, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Skin artist, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Work song, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Young woman blues, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - After the session/The combo, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Black and white/The black and the white, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - The Bop/The rest, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - The Bop boys, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Country club dance, Tuxedo Park NY, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Detroit Breadline, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - French horn, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Georgia chain gang, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Looking for a gig, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Noon at the Dôme, Paris, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Prison band – Georgia/Prison band, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - The rootless, Ohio, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Shimmy/I wish I could shimmy like my sister Kate, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - West Coast jazz (L.A.)/Improvising, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Untitled [man sleeping on table with horn and bottle], undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - General subjects
    - LA court/the real criminal is the public defender, 1935/1965 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Men of good will/Paris court [France], 1927 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Rainy day, St. Paul's [London, England], 1929 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Stage Backdrop Collages, 1952-1955; Series V; 1.67; (1 box)
  Arranged in chronological order.
  Series V contains a set of seven collages that Longstreet donated to the library in 1992. In his accompanying letter he wrote, "In the 1950s Kenneth Rexroth and other advant [sic] garde figures were going up + down the West Coast reciting poetry to Jazz: Whitman, Dickinson, Eliot, Ginsberg, e.e. cummings, Millay and others. For these recitings I did a series of stage back drops, abstract versions of American poets and Jazz music." He added that these are "the original designs from which the stage back drops were painted," but on two of the collages he wrote "slide projection," suggesting that at least those two works had been photographed and projected behind the poets. The dates cited in the box and folder list are those written on the collages by the artist, though they are most likely assigned from memory and may not always be reliable. As an example, Longstreet dated his design for the recital of Ginsberg's "Howl" as 1953, although its live debut was in 1955 and its publication came 1956. In addition, the Los Angeles Times only documents Rexroth and Lawrence Lipton holding similar poetry and jazz events in the late fall of 1957.
  The performers and works cited on the collages are: Val Burton, Kenneth Rexroth and chorus, reading selections from Walt Whitman's "Leaves of Grass" to Joe Zawinul's "The Rise and Fall of the Third Stream;" unidentified readers presenting Allen Ginsberg's "Howl" to Bessie Smith's "I'd Rather be Dead and Buried" and T.S. Eliot's "The Waste Land" to the recording "Jazz at Massey Hall" (featuring Dizzy Gillespie, Charlie Parker, Bud Powell, Charles Mingus, and Max Roach); Lawrence Lipton and Group reading selections from Emily Dickinson to Benny Goodman's "The Japanese Sandman;" the Pasadena Actors Group reading selections from Langston Hughes to James P. Johnson's "Boogie Woogie Stride;" the Beverly [Hills?] Jazz Society reading William Butler Yeats' "Sailing to Byzantium" to Dizzy Gillespie's "Anthropology;" and Lawrence Lipton, Val Burton and others reading the King James Version of "The Song of Songs" to King Oliver's "Frankie and Johnny."
  - Joe Zawinul and Walt Whitman, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Bessie Smith and Allen Ginsberg, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - "Jazz at Massey Hall" and T.S. Eliot, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Benny Goodman and Emily Dickinson, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - James P. Johnson and Langston Hughes, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Dizzy Gillespie and William Butler Yeats, undated (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - King Oliver and the Bible, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Proofs of plates from Knaurs Jazzlexikon (in Series II), 1957 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Poster from exhibition in Breda, Netherlands (in Series II), 1976 (Box 6, Folder 33)